populateNoE est une commande appelable via la commande manage.py de Django et permettant de charger des données dans la base de données. Il s'agit d'un loader, implémenté sur le branche feature-2 de NoE

Utilisation

La commande s'utilise de la façon suivante :

python manage.py populateNoE table [--clear-table] --data-dir dir

table : Le nom de la table. Pour peupler toutes les tables vous pouvez utiliser “all”.

-data-dir : Le repertoire contenant les différents fichiers de configuration

-clear-table : Argument optionnel pour vider la table choisie avant de la peupler.

Pour plus d'informations merci de regarder l'aide :

python manage.py populateNoE --help

Implémentation

Le fichier contenant le code source se nomme populateNoE.py et est placé dans NoE/core/management/commands.

Il contient une classe Command qui hérite de BaseCommand. Cette dernière implémente la méthode add_arguments pour gérer les options et handle qui est la méthode appelée lors de l’exécution du programme.

Pour plus d'informations sur l'écriture de commandes personnalisées, merci de se reporter à la doc de Django.

Remplissage de la BDD

Répertoire data-dir

On utilise normalement le répertoire

 $OWNCLOUD/NoE/Data

Ce répertoire contient des fichiers (généralement au format .csv) qui vont être parsées afin de peupler la base de données.

Storages

La partie stockage est composée de plusieurs fichiers :

Q00-11-V01_Equipement_BIOASTER1.csv : L'équivalent du fichier Q00-11-V01_Equipement_BIOASTER1.xlsx se trouvant dans M:/ Partage → 15 QSI → 03 Metrologie Maintenance ou /run/user/1001/gvfs/smb-share:server=b1winficp01.bioaster.local,share=data/01_Partage/15_QSI/03_Metrologie_Maintenance pour les linuxiens

laboPhysiques.csv : Une liste de laboratoires avec leur BSL et leur étage. Ce fichier contient les informations présentes sur la page Laboratoires physiques mise à jour par la NeT.

final_storages_drawers.csv : Fichier contenant les éventuels tiroirs des frigos. Il résulte de la concaténation (et curation manuelle) de chaque fichier envoyé par chaque expert de la NeT. Les fichiers individuels sont dans le sous répertoire NETStorages

Si un frigo n'est pas dans le même laboratoire entre le fichier Q00-11-V01_Equipement_BIOASTER1.csv et final_storages_drawers.csv, l'algorithme prendra le laboratoire indiqué dans final_storages_drawers.csv

Lesson03 SQL basics

3.1 SQL Types

Each column in a database table is required to have a name and a data type. The complete types docs of postgresql can be found https://www.postgresql.org/docs/11/datatype.html

3.1.1 SQL General Data Types

Boolean

Character types such as char, varchar, and text.

Numeric types such as integer and floating-point number.

Temporal types such as date, time, timestamp, and interval

Enumerated Types

Binary Objects (BLOB)

Boolean

A column of boolean type can have three states: TRUE, FALSE and NULL. In RDBMs, the value of type boolean is quite flexible, TRUE ⇒ 't', 'true', 'y', 'yes','1' ; FALSE ⇒ 'f','false','n','no','0'; We can use logical operator on them: =,<>(not equal),not,and,or.

Character types

We have three primary character types:

character(n) or char(n): fixed-length, blank padded

character varying(n) or varchar(n): variable-length with limit

text(varchar): variable unlimited length

Both char(n) and varchar(n) can store up to n characters in length(n is a positive integer), if you try to store a longer string in the column, it will issue an error.

In postgresql server, there is no performance difference among three character types. In most situation, you should use text or varchar. If you want postgresql help you to check the length limit, then use varchar(n).

Numeric Types

Integers: SQL only specifies the integer types integer (or int), smallint, and bigint. The type names int2, int4, and int8 are extensions, which are also used by some RDBMS.

Arbitrary-Precision Numbers: The types decimal and numeric are equivalent. Both types are part of the SQL standard. Calculations with numeric values yield exact results whenever possible.

Floating-Points Types: These types are usually implementations of IEEE Standard 754 for Binary Floating-Point Arithmetic (single and double precision, respectively). The data types real and double precision are inexact.

Serial Types: The data types smallserial, serial and bigserial are not true types, but merely a notational convenience for creating unique identifier columns. They’re similar to the AUTO_INCREMENT property supported by some other RDBMS.

NAME | STORAGE SIZE | DESCRIPTION | RANGE
Smallint | 2 bytes | small-range integer | -32768 to +32767
Integer | 4 bytes | typical choice for integer | -2147483648 to +2147483647
Bigint | 8 bytes | large-range integer | -9223372036854775808 to +9223372036854775807
decimal | variable | user-specified precision,exact | up to 131072 digits before the decimal point; up to 16383 digits after the decimal point
numeric | variable | user-specified precision,exact | up to 131072 digits before the decimal point;up to 16383 digits after the decimal point
real | 4 bytes | variable-precision,inexact | 6 decimal digits precision
double precision | 8 bytes | variable-precision,inexact | 15 decimal digits precision
smallserial | 2 bytes | small autoincrementing integer | 1 to 32767
serial | 4 bytes | autoincrementing integer | 1 to 2147483647
bigserial | 8 bytes | large autoincrementing integer | 1 to 9223372036854775807

Temporal types

Cover SQL date and time type full set. Dates are counted according to the Gregorian calendar, even in years before that calendar was introduced.

NAME | STORAGE SIZE | DESCRIPTION | LOW VALUE | HIGH VALUE |
timestamp [ (p) ][ without time zone ] | 8 bytes | both date and time (no time zone) | 4713 BC | 294276 AD | 1 microsecond
timestamp [ (p) ] with time zone | 8 bytes | both date and time, with time zone | 4713 BC | 294276 AD | 1 microsecond
date | 4 bytes | date (no time of day) | 4713 BC | 5874897 AD | 1 day
time [ (p) ][ without time zone ] | 8 bytes | time of day (no date) | 00:00:00 | 24:00:00 | 1 microsecond
time [ (p) ] with time zone | 12 bytes | time of day (no date), with time zone | 00:00:00+1459 | 24:00:00-1459 | 1 microsecond
interval [ fields ] [ (p) ] | 16 bytes | time interval | -178000000 years | 178000000 years | 1 microsecond

Value p specifies the number of fractional digits retained in the seconds' field. Any date or time literal input needs to be enclosed in single quotes, like text strings.

Enumerated Types

Enumerated (enum) types are data types that comprise a static, ordered set of values. For example: ('sad', 'ok', 'happy')

BLOB

The SQL standard defines a different binary string type, called BLOB or BINARY LARGE OBJECT. MySQL and ORACLE give the same name. PostgreSQL has type bytea. The input format is different but the provided functions and operators are mostly the same

3.1.2 Other Types

Monetary Type

Geometric Types

Network address

UUID for storing Universally Unique Identifiers

XML Type

JSON Type

Array for storing array strings, numbers, etc.

Composite Types

Range Types

3.1.3 The Null Value

NULL is not a value, it is a special marker to indicate that a data value does not exist in the database. It is used to signify missing or unknown values. The SQL keyword NULL is used to indicate these values. NULL really isn’t a specific value as much as it is an indicator. Don’t think of NULL as similar to zero or blank or false, it isn’t the same.

You must use the IS NULL or IS NOT NULL operators to check for a NULL value. It is not possible to test for NULL values with comparison operators, such as =, <, or <>.

3.2 SQL coding convention

The below list is the general sql coding convention

Use comments to describe what SQL does

Put each major SQL statement on a new line

Put SQL keywords, built-in function and data types in the uppercase. Use CamelCase capitalization and do not separate name parts with underscores or use lower case and underscores to separate name parts.

Set standard abbreviations for frequently used objects, such as tbl for tables or idx for indexes

Use single quotation for characters, strings, binary and Unicode

Set a rule for naming aliases

Use indenting to align wrapped long lines

Use parentheses in complex mathematical expressions

Be consistent with indentation – use either tab or space

Don’t avoid using line breaks to improve readability

Code grouping – keep the lines that execute a certain task in separate code blocks

IMPORTANT NOTE: SQL language is case insensitive (for the keywords).

3.3 Data manipulation language

SELECT : Retrieve certain records (get data) from a database

INSERT : Creates a record (insert data) into a table

UPDATE : Modifies records (update data) within a table

DELETE : Delete records (remove data) from a database table

MERGE : (UPSERT) Update a record if it already exists, otherwise, inserts a new row in a table.

3.4 Data definition language

CREATE: Create the database or its objects (like table, index, function, views, store procedure and triggers)

DROP: Deletes objects (like an entire table, a view of a table or other objects)

ALTER: Modifies an existing database object, such as a table

RENAME: Rename an object existing in the database

TRUNCATE: Remove all records from a table. All corresponded spaces allocated for them are released

COMMENT: Define or change the comment of an object

Create

Create is one of the most used command in sql. In postgresql, you can create 42 different objects with create command.

# create database
CREATE DATABASE database_name [parameters]
# create table
CREATE [TEMPORARY] TABLE [IF NOT EXISTS] table_name [parameters]
# create view
CREATE [OR REPLACE] [TEMP | TEMPORARY] [RECURSIVE] view_name [parameters]
# create index
CREATE [ CONCURRENTLY ] [ [ IF NOT EXISTS ] INDEX index_name [parameters]

CREATE CAST — define a new cast
CREATE EVENT TRIGGER — define a new event trigger
CREATE EXTENSION — install an extension
CREATE FUNCTION — define a new function
CREATE GROUP — define a new database role
CREATE SEQUENCE — define a new sequence generator
CREATE STATISTICS — define extended statistics
CREATE TRIGGER — define a new trigger
CREATE TYPE — define a new data type
CREATE USER — define a new database role
CREATE VIEW — define a new view

Create table

The most used CREATE statement in SQL is for tables:

CREATE [TEMPORARY] TABLE [IF NOT EXISTS] table_name (
column_name TYPE column_constraint,
table_constraint table_constraint,
);

List the column names, their data types, and constraints. A table may have multiple columns separated by a comma (,).

We have two types of constraints in create command. Table constraints, that defines rules for the data in the table. Column constraints defines rules for the data in the column.

The following are the commonly used column constraints in SQL:

NOT NULL – the value of the column cannot be NULL.

UNIQUE – the value of the column must be unique across the whole table. SQL standard only allows one NULL value in the column that has the UNIQUE constraint (PostgreSQL treats each NULL value to be unique so such column can have many NULL values)

PRIMARY KEY – this constraint is the combination of NOT NULL and UNIQUE constraints. You can define one column as PRIMARY KEY by using column level constraint. In case the primary key contains multiple columns, you must use the table-level constraint.

CHECK – enables to check a condition when you insert or update data. For example, the values in the price column of the product table must be positive values.

REFERENCES – constrains the value of the column that exists in a column in another table. You use REFERENCES to define the foreign key constraint.

The table constraints are similar to column constraints except that they are applied to the entire table rather than to an individual column.

The following are the table constraints:

UNIQUE (column_list) – to force the value stored in the columns listed inside the parentheses to be unique.

PRIMARY KEY(column_list) – to define the primary key that consists of multiple columns.

CHECK (condition) – to check a condition when inserting or updating data.

REFERENCES – to constrain the value stored in the column that must exist in a column in another table.

Example of create table

Suppose we have a system to manage user account and role. So we need to create three tables:

account

role

account_role

The account table has the following columns with the corresponding constraints:

user_id – primary key

username – unique and not null

password – not null

email – unique and not null

created_on – not null

last_login – null

The role table has the following columns with the corresponding constraints:

role_id - primary key

role_name - unique and not null

The account_role table is an association table which links an account to 0 or n roles, it has the following columns with the corresponding constraints:

user_id - the foreign key reference to column user_id of account table

role_id - the foreign key reference to column role_id of role table

grant_date - timestamp without time zone

(user_id,role_id) - primary key

CREATE TABLE account (
user_id serial PRIMARY KEY,
username VARCHAR (50) UNIQUE NOT NULL,
password VARCHAR (50) NOT NULL,
email VARCHAR (355) UNIQUE NOT NULL,
created_on TIMESTAMP NOT NULL,
last_login TIMESTAMP
);

CREATE TABLE role(
role_id serial PRIMARY KEY,
role_name VARCHAR (255)
UNIQUE NOT NULL
);

CREATE TABLE account_role (
user_id integer NOT NULL,
role_id integer NOT NULL,
grant_date timestamp without time zone,
PRIMARY KEY (user_id, role_id),
CONSTRAINT account_role_role_id_fkey FOREIGN KEY (role_id)
REFERENCES role (role_id) MATCH SIMPLE
ON UPDATE NO ACTION ON DELETE NO ACTION,
CONSTRAINT account_role_user_id_fkey FOREIGN KEY (user_id)
REFERENCES account (user_id) MATCH SIMPLE
ON UPDATE NO ACTION ON DELETE NO ACTION
);

Drop

The drop statement in SQL is used to delete created database objects. You can use the drop statement in SQL to delete databases, tables, indexes, etc. In PostgreSQL, we have 43 commands to delete existing objects. The Below list contains some of the most common used drop commands:

# delete database
DROP DATABASE [ IF EXISTS ] database_name
# delete table, add cascade if 
DROP TABLE [ IF EXISTS ] table_name [ CASCADE ]
# delete view
DROP VIEW [ IF EXISTS ] table_name [ CASCADE ]
# delete index
DROP INDEX [ IF EXISTS ] index_name [ CASCADE ]
DROP CAST — remove a cast
DROP EXTENSION — remove an extension
DROP FOREIGN TABLE — remove a foreign table
DROP FUNCTION — remove a function
DROP LANGUAGE — remove a procedural language
DROP OPERATOR — remove an operator
DROP OWNED — remove database objects owned by a database role
DROP SCHEMA — remove a schema
DROP SEQUENCE — remove a sequence
DROP TRIGGER — remove a trigger
DROP TYPE — remove a data type

drop table

The most used drop statement in sql is for tables. If you drop a table, all the rows in the table are deleted and the table structure is removed from the database. We can also use the drop statement in alter table statement to remove columns from tables.

According to the sql standard, specifying either RESTRICT or CASCADE is required in a drop command. When cascade is specified in a drop command, it will automatically drop objects that depend on the table (e.g. views, constraints or any other objects)

In a complex database, many tables have foreign key constraints, or views, triggers, functions, etc. When you do drop table toto, you will often receive errors such as “unique/primary keys in table referenced by foreign keys”. So we have to use CASCADE to remove the table. But keep in mind when you do “drop table toto cascad;”, all the dependent objects will be removed, as will any objects that depend on them, recursively.

Drop example

We retake the example of create table, suppose the table of account, role, account_role are already created. Now we want to drop table account

Alter

Modifies the definition of an existing database object, such as a table. There are 42 different ALTER commands in PostgreSQL. ALTER TABLE changes the definition of an existing table. There are several subforms. Note that the lock level required may differ for each subform.

Examples of alter table columns

ALTER TABLE table_name ADD COLUMN column_name data_type;
ALTER TABLE table_name DROP COLUMN [IF EXISTS] column_name [RESTRICT | CASCADE];

We can also modify table constraints with alter

# Create a new constraint
ALTER TABLE table_name ADD table_constraint [ NOT VALID ]

# Apply the newly created constraints on the table which was previously created as NOT VALID, by scanning the table to ensure there are no rows for which the constraint is not satisfied.
ALTER TABLE table_name VALIDATE CONSTRAINT constraint_name

# drop constraint 
ALTER TABLE table_name DROP CONSTRAINT [IF EXISTS] constraint_name [RESTRICT | CASCADE]

Note: ALTER TABLE that acts on a single table can be combined into a list of multiple alterations to be applied together. For example, it is possible to add several columns and/or alter the type of several columns in a single command.

Rename

Only three rename commands in postgresql

# Rename a column
ALTER TABLE [ IF EXISTS ] [ ONLY ] table_name RENAME [ COLUMN ] column_name TO new_column_name
# Rename a constraint
ALTER TABLE [ IF EXISTS ] [ ONLY ] table_name RENAME CONSTRAINT constraint_name TO new_constraint_name
# Rename a table
ALTER TABLE [ IF EXISTS ] name RENAME TO new_name

Note: When renaming a constraint that has an underlying index, the index is renamed as well

TRUNCATE

You can use SQL TRUNCATE TABLE statement to remove all data from large tables quickly. To remove all data from a table, you use the DELETE statement. However, for a large table, it is more efficient to use the TRUNCATE TABLE statement. The TRUNCATE TABLE statement removes all rows from a table without scanning it.

TRUNCATE TABLE table_name1, table_name2,

The advantage of truncate compare to drop table:

Reclaim Space immediately

No impact on transaction logs

Comment

There is no COMMENT command in the SQL standard. You can use a SQL COMMENT statement to store a comment about a database object. Only one comment string is stored for each object, so to modify a comment, issue a new COMMENT command for the same object. To remove a comment, write NULL in place of the text string.

COMMENT ON object_name IS 'text'

Préparation de la réunion AD

A la 1re connexion de la journée :

l'utilisateur clique sur le bouton login

Il est renvoyé à la frontale de Shibboleth

Il se connecte avec ses identifiants AD

Shibboleth le renvoie à sa page d'accueil du LIMS

Shibboleth crée un cookie valable pendant un temps t.

Le schéma est le même que pour BCOM, sans la partie ACAST.

Attention! Le LIMS ne gère pas le mot de passe ! C'est au service informatique de la faire. On peut éventuellement faire ça depuis Shibboleth ?

Classification des echantillons

[NS] Transmettre la classification à l'UTEC1 pour avis. Peut-on reprendre la classification de Biospecimens? De bMx?

Cas des échantillons de type fécès : (1) on reçoit un échantillon de type fécès dont on extrait les bactérie. (2) les bactérie sont cultivées et prennent le type culture (3) la bioentité d'origine des bactérie reste l'individu d'où proviennent les fécès. Le numéro de génération des cultures pourra être précisé dans le formulaire Web, puis rajouté dans l'alias de l'échantillon.

Réunion du 23 Février 2017

Personnes présentes

YM

CD

Avancées

Mettre configuration de auth mode et port en variables → C'est fait, diapo mises à jour en conséquences.

Implémentation de la réinitialisation du mot de passe par e-mail. (démo ?)

Voir les specs et autres documentations pour voir quelles étapes du workflow envoient un mail ou non. → Contacter KL et BR ? → On doit pouvoir configurer si l'étape envoie un mail ou non ainsi que le contenu et l'objet du mail en backoffice. Une table 'email' a été ajoutée à la BDD. Chaque étape du workflow doit montrer un pop avec un check box à cocher si on veut envoyer un e-mail → ça devient compliqué pour les workflow par échantillon.

Reste à faire

Continuer les emails.

Diapo pour la réunion d'équipe de mercredi (le plan est fait).

Mettre à jour la base de données sur sql designer.

Reprendre le formulaire “mon compte”

Régler bug de la Réunion du 16 Février 2017

À faire pour la prochaine réunion

Finir la partie email :

Ajouter bouton “mot de passe oublié”

Lier la table Step à Email → Migration + inclure dans le popup en frontend

Ajouter un compteur de tentatives de login pour un nombre de saisi infructueux

Commencer à contacter KL pour la partie import massif

Faire diapo pour la réunion d'équipe du 01/03/2017

Autre

ZooKeeper 07: ZooKeeper best practice and optimisation

Some of the best practices of running and managing a ZooKeeper ensemble are shown here:

The ZooKeeper data directory contains the snapshot and transactional log files. It is a good practice to periodically clean up the directory if the autopurge option is not enabled. Also, an administrator might want to keep a backup of these files, depending on the application needs. However, since ZooKeeper is a replicated service, we need to back up the data of only one of the servers in the ensemble.

ZooKeeper uses Apache log4j as its logging infrastructure. As the logfiles grow bigger in size, it is recommended that you set the auto-rollover of the logfiles using the in-built log4j feature for ZooKeeper logs.

The list of ZooKeeper servers used by the clients in their connection strings must match the list of ZooKeeper servers that each ZooKeeper server has. Strange behaviors might occur if the lists don't match.

The server lists in each Zookeeper server configuration file should be consistent with the other members of the ensemble.

As already mentioned, the ZooKeeper transaction log must be configured in a dedicated device. This is very important to achieve the best performance from ZooKeeper.

Check the status of zookeeper server from client side

Zookeeper provides a list of four-letter commends for the client. These commands can be issued through telnet or nc at the client-side.

conf: This print details about server configuration parameters such as clientPort, dataDir, tickTime, and so on.

cons: This lists the full connection/session details for all clients connected to this server.

crst : This resets connection/session statistics for all connections.

dump: This lists the outstanding sessions and ephemeral nodes. This only works on the leader.

envi: Lists the environment parameters

ruok: This checks whether the server is running without any error. The server will respond with imok if it is running. If the server is in some error state, it will not respond to this command.

srst: This resets the server statistics.

stat: This provides information on the current status of the server and the list of connected clients.

srvr: This provides the same information as the stat command, except the list of connected clients.

wchs: This provides brief information on watches for the server.

wchc: This provides detailed information on watches for the server, sorted by sessions (connections), showing a list of sessions with associated watches (paths).

wchp: This provides detailed information on watches for the server, sorted by paths (znodes). This shows a list of paths with associated sessions.

mntr: This outputs a list of variables that can be used to monitor the health of the cluster.

Important note: By default only srvr is in the white list(allow list). Others are not, if you want to expose them to client side, you need to add them to the white list.

# not allowed
[pliu@localhost ~]$ echo ruok | nc localhost 2181
ruok is not executed because it is not in the whitelist.

[pliu@localhost ~]$ echo srvr | nc localhost 2181
Zookeeper version: 3.6.1--104dcb3e3fb464b30c5186d229e00af9f332524b, built on 04/21/2020 15:01 GMT
Latency min/avg/max: 0/0.33/7
Received: 696
Sent: 695
Connections: 1
Outstanding: 0
Zxid: 0x159
Mode: standalone
Node count: 14

Check status from the sever side

ZooKeeper provides for extensive monitoring and management capabilities with Java Management Extensions (JMX). We will look at using jconsole, a simple management console available with JMX, to explore ZooKeeper management.

Starting ZooKeeper with JMX enabled

The class org.apache.zookeeper.server.quorum.QuorumPeerMain will start a JMX manageable ZooKeeper server. This class registers the proper MBeans during initalization to support JMX monitoring and management of the instance. See bin/zkServer.sh for one example of starting ZooKeeper using QuorumPeerMain.

Jconsole

jconsole can be find in $JAVA_HOME/bin. Run it on the same server same jvm, you should see the org.apache.ZooKeeperService

The MBeans tab shows detailed information on ZooKeeper's internal state, such as details of the clients connected and the various attributes and details about operations done in the ZooKeeper namespace. Managed Beans (MBeans) is a very elegant and flexible way to expose internal information on the ZooKeeper server through JMX.

More details on the various MBeans available for ZooKeeper management and monitoring can be found at https://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/trunk/zookeeperJMX.html

Lesson02: Installing and configuring kafka

2.0 Prerequise

2.0.1 Install JDK

Kafka needs JDK or JRE to run. So the first step is to install jdk.

2.0.2 Install zookeeper

A critical dependency of Apache Kafka is Apache Zookeeper, which is a distributed configuration and synchronization service. Kafka uses ZooKeeper for:

leadership election of Kafka Broker to elect Controller: The first arrived broker creates /kafka/controller znode in zk. The other broker will fail because it already exists.

partition replication leader/follower election

discover new coming brokers

stores basic metadata in Zookeeper such as information about topics(topic-partition pairs), brokers, consumer offsets (queue readers) and so on.

ETc.

Since all the critical information is stored in the Zookeeper and it normally replicates this data across its ensemble, failure of Kafka broker / Zookeeper does not affect the state of the Kafka cluster. Kafka will restore the state, once the Zookeeper restarts. This gives zero downtime for Kafka. The leader election between the Kafka broker is also done by using Zookeeper in the event of leader failure.

To learn more about ZooKeeper: ZooKeeper docs

2.0.3 Hardware requirement

At least 4GB of RAM on the server. Installations without this amount of RAM may cause the Kafka service to fail, with the Java virtual machine (JVM) throwing an “Out Of Memory” exception during startup.

2.1 Creating a User for Kafka

# create a system user Kafka with a home dir
useradd -r kafka -m

# add Kafka to sudoer group
usermod -aG wheel kafka

# login as kafka
su -l kafka

2.2 Downloading and Extracting the Kafka Binaries

Download the kafka binary from http://kafka.apache.org/downloads.html

Note that Kafka uses Scala, and it's binary is compiled based on certain version of Scala. For example, kafka_2.11-1.0.0 means this Kafka version 1.0.0 is compiled based on scala 2.11; kafka_2.12-2.5.0 means this kafka of version 2.5.0 is compiled based on scala 2.12. So before you chose your kafka binary version, you need to check the scala version which runs on your server.

Then place the binary in your server. I put it under “/opt/kafka”

mkdir /opt/kafka

cd /opt/kafka

# extract the binary
tar -xzvf kafka_2.12-2.5.0.tgz 

# change the name
mv kafka_2.12-2.5.0 kafka-2.5.0

# check the result
[root@localhost kafka-2.5.0]# pwd
/opt/kafka/kafka-2.5.0

2.3 Configuring the Kafka Server

The main config file of a Kafka broker is on the server.properties file. The default config is enough to run a standalone Kafka broker as a test server. But I still want to highlight some key configuration attributes.

【broker.id】
每个broker都必须自己设置的一个唯一id，可以在0~255之间. A good guideline is to set this value to something intrinsic to the host. For example, if your hostnames contain a unique number (such as host1.example.com , host2.example.com , etc.), that is a good choice for the broker.id value.

【log.dirs】
这个极为重要，kafka的所有数据就是写入这个目录下的磁盘文件中的，如果说机器上有多块物理硬盘，那么可以把多个目录挂载到不同的物理硬盘上，然后这里可以设置多个目录，这样kafka可以数据分散到多块物理硬盘，多个硬盘的磁头可以并行写，这样可以提升吞吐量。ps：多个目录用英文逗号分隔. If more than one path is specified(e.g. log.dirs=path1,path2), the broker will store partitions on them in a “least-used” fashion with one partition’s log segments stored within the same path. Note that the broker will place a new partition in the path that has the least number of partitions currently stored in it, not the least amount of disk space used in the following situations

【zookeeper.connect】
连接kafka底层的zookeeper集群的. The default configuration is localhost:2181.

【Listeners】
broker监听客户端发起请求的ip,端口号，默认是9092. It will get the value returned from ** java.net.InetAddress.getCanonicalHostName() if not configured**. The port number can be set to any available port by changing the port configuration parameter. Keep in mind that if a port lower than 1024 is chosen, Kafka must be started as root. Running Kafka as root is not a recommended configuration.

# open the config file
cd /opt/kafka/kafka_2.11-1.0.0/config
vim server.properties

The following is an example of minimum configuration

#in a single server with default zookeeper
broker.id=0
log.dirs=/tmp/kafka-logs
zookeeper.connect=localhost:2181
 
#in a cluster environment with multiple zookeeper instances
zookeeper.connect=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2181,hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2181,hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2181
broker.id=1 (2,3 in other two machines)
log.dirs=fs_on_disk1,fs_on_disk2

The above config is the minimun config to run kafka, you may need to dig more.

2.4 Creating Systemd Unit Files and Starting the Kafka Server

We need to create the systemd service file for Kafka. As Kafka requires ZooKeeper to manage its cluster state and configuration. We need to make sure we have a systemd service file for Zookeeper first. Suppose we have it in /etc/systemd/system/zk.service

Our Kafka systemd file looks like this:

[Unit]
Requires=zk.service
After=zk.service

[Service]
Type=forking
WorkingDirectory=/opt/kafka/kafka-2.5.0
User=kafka
Group=kafka
ExecStart=/opt/kafka/kafka-2.5.0/bin/kafka-server-start.sh /opt/kafka/kafka-2.5.0/config/server.properties > /var/log/kafka/kafka.log 2>&1
ExecStop=/opt/kafka/kafka-2.5.0/bin/kafka-server-stop.sh
Restart=on-abnormal

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target

The Unit part will ensure that zookeeper gets started automatically when the kafa service starts.

Run the daemon

sudo systemctl start/stop/status kafka

# run daemon at system startup
sudo systemctl enable kafka

2.5 Testing the Installation

To test the kafka server (with one broker). Make sure the zookeeper is running before you run this command.

sh bin/kafka-server-start.sh config/server.properties

2.5.1 Create a topic

Create a topic with one partition and three replication

#create a topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --create --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org --replication-factor 3 --partitions 1 --topic test-topic
Created topic "test-topic".

#check status of a topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org --topic test-topic
Topic:test-topic	PartitionCount:1	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 0	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,3,1

Create a topic with three partitions and three replication

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --create --zookeeper localhost:2181 --replication-factor 3 --partitions 3 --topic Hello-Kafka

Created topic "Hello-Kafka".

#get status of the topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --topic Hello-Kafka
Topic:Hello-Kafka	PartitionCount:3	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: Hello-Kafka	Partition: 0	Leader: 1	Replicas: 1,2,3	Isr: 1
	Topic: Hello-Kafka	Partition: 1	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,3,1
	Topic: Hello-Kafka	Partition: 2	Leader: 3	Replicas: 3,1,2	Isr: 3,1,2

List all topic in one broker

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --list --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181
Hello-Kafka
test-topic

2.5.2 Start producer to send messages

# In the broker-list, you could put one or more kafka brokers
# In this example, we use only one, the name of the broker is defined in server.properties  
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-console-producer.sh --broker-list hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:9092 --topic Hello-Kafka
#now you are in producer consol, all the text you enter below will be published in topic Hello-Kafka
>hello
>my first message
>my second message
>my third message

2.5.3 Start two consumers to receive messages

###in server hadoop-dn1.bioaster.org
hadoop@CCLinDataWHD02 bin]$ sh kafka-console-consumer.sh --bootstrap-server localhost:9092 --topic Hello-Kafka --from-beginning
Using the ConsoleConsumer with old consumer is deprecated and will be removed in a future major release. Consider using the new consumer by passing [bootstrap-server] instead of [zookeeper].
hello
my first message
my second message
my third message
my fouth message
my fifth message


###in server hadoop-dn2.bioaster.org
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD03-0 bin]$ sh kafka-console-consumer.sh --bootstrap-server localhost:9092 --topic Hello-Kafka --from-beginning
Using the ConsoleConsumer with old consumer is deprecated and will be removed in a future major release. Consider using the new consumer by passing [bootstrap-server] instead of [zookeeper].
hello
my third message
my first message
my second message
my fouth message
my fifth message


##You could notice, if your consumer connecter after many message has been published
##the order may not be correct. But the latest message will be correct

2.5.4 Close the test

When you are done testing, press CTRL+C to stop the producer and consumer scripts.

To delete the topic use the following command

[root@localhost kafka-2.5.0]# bin/kafka-topics.sh --zookeeper localhost:2181 --delete --topic pengfeiTest
Topic pengfeiTest is marked for deletion.
Note: This will have no impact if delete.topic.enable is not set to true.

2.6 Setting Up a Multi-Node Cluster

There are three possible scenarios:

Multi brokers on single servers

Single brokers on multi-servers

Multi brokers on multi-servers

2.6.1 Multi brokers on single servers

For setting up multiple brokers on a single node, different server property files are required for each broker. Each property file will define unique, different values for the following properties:

broker.id

port

log.dir

For example, if we want to run three brokers on a single server, we need to create three config files server1.properties, server2.properties, server3.properties.

broker.id=1
listeners = PLAINTEXT://your.host.name:9093
log.dir=/tmp/kafka-logs-1

broker.id=2
listeners = PLAINTEXT://your.host.name:9094
log.dir=/tmp/kafka-logs-2

broker.id=3
listeners = PLAINTEXT://your.host.name:9095
log.dir=/tmp/kafka-logs-3

We can run the three instances of the broker with the following command

#run broker1
bin/kafka-server-start.sh config/server1.properties

#run broker2
bin/kafka-server-start.sh config/server1.properties

#run broker3
bin/kafka-server-start.sh config/server1.properties

2.6.2 Single broker on multi nodes

This is very simple, all these brokers can have the exact same configuration except the broker.id.

Zookeeper configuration

If you want your Kafka broker to connect to multiple zookeeper servers. In zookeeper.connect, you can use comma-separated string listing the IP addresses and port numbers of all the ZooKeeper instances.

For example

//Kafka uses three zk instances
zookeeper.connect=zk1.pengfei.org:2181,zk2.pengfei.org:2181,zk3.pengfei.org:2181

2.7 Restricting the Kafka User

# Remove the kafka user from the sudo group:
sudo gpasswd -d kafka wheel

# To further improve your Kafka server’s security, lock the kafka user’s password using the passwd command. This makes sure that nobody can directly log into the server using this account:
sudo passwd kafka -l

# At this point, only root or a sudo user can log in as kafka by typing in the following command:
sudo su - Kafka

# In the future, if you want to unlock it, use passwd with the -u option:
sudo passwd kafka -u

2.8 Basic topic operations (Optional)

2.8.1 List all topics and show details of a topic

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --list --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181
Hello-Kafka
test-topic

#show detail of topic test-topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --topic test-topic
Topic:test-topic	PartitionCount:1	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 0	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,1,3

#we know that it has one partition and 3 replicas

2.8.2 Change the partition number of a topic

#Now we want to change the partition from one to two
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --alter --topic test-topic --partitions 2
WARNING: If partitions are increased for a topic that has a key, the partition logic or ordering of the messages will be affected
Adding partitions succeeded!

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --topic test-topic
Topic:test-topic	PartitionCount:2	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 0	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,1,3
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 1	Leader: 3	Replicas: 3,2,1	Isr: 3,2,1

2.8.3 Delet a topic

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --delete --topic test-topic
Topic test-topic is marked for deletion.
Note: This will have no impact if delete.topic.enable is not set to true.
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --list --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181
Hello-Kafka

2.9 Kafka runs starts and runs the zookeeper (Optional)

if your zookeeper cluster already running or controlled by zookeeper, you don't need to chage the config of /opt/kafka/kafka_2.11-1.0.0/config/zookeeper.properties

if you want to use kafka to control the zookeeper daemon, you need to edit the zookeeper.properties

Here is an example

# the directory where the snapshot is stored.
dataDir=/opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/data
# the port at which the clients will connect
clientPort=2181
# disable the per-ip limit on the number of connections since this is a non-production config
maxClientCnxns=0

# The number of milliseconds of each tick
tickTime=2000

# The number of ticks that the initial synchronization phase can take
initLimit=10

# The number of ticks that can pass between 
# sending a request and getting an acknowledgement
syncLimit=5

#zoo servers
server.1=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.2=hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.3=hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2888:3888

It's the same as the zoo.cfg in zookeeper

# The number of milliseconds of each tick
tickTime=2000
# The number of ticks that the initial 
# synchronization phase can take
#initLimit=10
initLimit=5
# The number of ticks that can pass between 
# sending a request and getting an acknowledgement
#syncLimit=5
syncLimit=5
# the directory where the snapshot is stored.
# do not use /tmp for storage, /tmp here is just 
# example sakes.
dataDir=/opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/data
# the port at which the clients will connect
clientPort=2181
# the maximum number of client connections.
# increase this if you need to handle more clients
#maxClientCnxns=60
#
# Be sure to read the maintenance section of the 
# administrator guide before turning on autopurge.
#
# http://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/current/zookeeperAdmin.html#sc_maintenance
#
# The number of snapshots to retain in dataDir
#autopurge.snapRetainCount=3
# Purge task interval in hours
# Set to "0" to disable auto purge feature
#autopurge.purgeInterval=1

server.1=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.2=hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.3=hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2888:3888

To run the zookeeper daemon in kafak

cd /opt/kafka/kafka_2.11-1.0.0
sh bin/zookeeper-server-start.sh config/zookeeper.properties

Zookeeper

Installation and configuration

Suppose we have zookeeper installed under /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10

and we have three server in the zookeeper cluster.

hadoop-nn.pengfei.org

hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org

hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org

vim /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/conf/zoo.cfg

#put the following config

tickTime=2000
dataDir=/tmp/zoo_data
clientPort=2181
initLimit=5
syncLimit=2
server.1=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.2=hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.3=hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2888:3888

The dataDir is the directory used by Zookeeper to store data.

The initLimit property is used to specify the maximum amount of time Zookeeper servers have to connect to the leader. When you are processing large amounts of data just increase this value as required.

The property syncLimit is used to fix allowable amount of time a server can be out of sync with leader.

The properties server.1, server.2 and server.3 specify the servers that form the Zookeeper service. Then you specify the host name of each of the servers followed by the port numbers 2888 and 3888. These ports are used for peer to peer communication. The first (2888) followers use to connect to the leader, and the second (3888) is for leader election.

To make each server aware of the other servers in the ensemble you use a myid file that is placed in the data directory of each server. This file contains only a unique value between 1 and 255 which corresponds to the value specified in zoo.cfg file. For example for server.1 the myid file only contains the value 1.

In our example, the myid file should be under /tmp/zoo_data

Starting/stoping zookeeper service

#start the zookeeper service daemon
sh /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/bin/zkServer.sh start

#check the daemon status
sh /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/bin/zkServer.sh status

#for a follower, the output is like this
ZooKeeper JMX enabled by default
Using config: /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/bin/../conf/zoo.cfg
Mode: follower

#for a leader, the output is like this
ZooKeeper JMX enabled by default
Using config: /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/bin/../conf/zoo.cfg
Mode: leader

#stop the daemon
sh /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/bin/zkServer.sh stop

Now we are all set for the zookeeper service, in order to stop or start the zookeeper daemon, you need to execute the shell command on all nodes.

A CLI is available to connect to the server and issue commands. To start it use the command below

# this starts a zookeeper client connect to a zookeeper server
sh /opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/bin/zkCli.sh -server 127.0.0.1:2181

What a distributed system is and its characteristics

Defining a distributed system

A distributed system is defined as a software system that is composed of independent computing entities linked together by a computer network whose components communicate and coordinate with each other to achieve a common goal.

Key characteristics of a distributed system

In order to identify a distributed system, here are the key characteristics that you need to look out for:

Resource sharing: This refers to the possibility of using the resources in the system, such as storage space, computing power, data, and services from anywhere, and so on.

Extendibility: This refers to the possibility of extending and improving the system incrementally, both from hardware and software perspectives.

Concurrency: This refers to the system's capability to be used by multiple users at the same time to accomplish the same task or different tasks

Performance and scalability: This ensures that the response time of the system doesn't degrade as the overall load increases

Fault tolerance: This ensures that the system is always available even if some of the components fail or operate in a degraded mode

Abstraction through APIs: This ensures that the system's individual components are concealed from the end-users, revealing only the end services to them

Key problems in a distributed system

The below list shows the key problems in a distributed system. But the most important problem is to make the participating computing entities, or independent programs, coordinate their actions.

Assumptions | Reality
The network is reliable | In reality, the network or the interconnection among the components can fail due to internal errors in the system or due to external factors such as power failure.
Latency is zero | Users of a distributed system can connect to it from anywhere in the globe, and it takes time to move data from one place to another. The network's quality of service also influences the latency of an application.
Bandwidth is infinite | Network bandwidth has improved many folds in the recent past, but this is not uniform across the world. Bandwidth depends on the type of the network (T1, LAN, WAN, mobile network, and so on).
The network is secure | The network is never secure. Often, systems face denial of-service attacks for not taking the security aspects of an application seriously during their design.
Topology doesn't change | In reality, the topology is never constant. Components get removed/added with time, and the system should have the ability to tolerate such changes.
There is one administrator | Distributed systems never function in isolation. They interact with other external systems for their functioning; this can be beyond administrative control.
Transport cost is zero | This is far from being true, as there is cost involved everywhere, from setting up the network to sending network packets from source to destination. The cost can be in the form of CPU cycles spent to actual dollars being paid to network service providers.
The network is homogeneous | A network is composed of a plethora of different entities. Thus, for an application to function correctly, it needs to be interoperable with various components, be it the type of network, operating system, or even the implementation languages.

Why zookeeper is useful for a distributed system

Apache ZooKeeper is an effort to develop a highly scalable, reliable, and robust centralized service to implement coordination in distributed systems that developers can straightaway use in their applications through a very simple interface to a centralized coordination service. It enables application developers to concentrate on the core business logic of their applications and rely entirely on the ZooKeeper service to get the coordination part correct and help them get going with their applications. It simplifies the development process, thus making it more nimble.

With ZooKeeper, developers can implement common distributed coordination tasks, such as the following:

Configuration management

Naming service

Distributed synchronization, such as locks and barriers

Cluster membership operations, such as detection of node leave/node join

Any distributed application needs these kinds of services one way or another, and implementing them from scratch often leads to bugs that cause the application to behave erratically. Zookeeper mitigates the need to implement coordination and synchronization services in distributed applications from scratch by providing simple and elegant primitives through a rich set of APIs.

Challenges of distributed applicatioins

Race condition: Sometimes there are two or more machines that are trying to perform a particular task, even when that task actually needs to be done only by a single machine at any given time.

Deadlock: In order to complete indefinitely, two or more operations waiting for each other.

Inconsistency: It means Partial failure of data.

Coodination in a distributed system

Coodinate/synchronize data

Let's take the example of doing configuration management for a distributed application that comprises multiple software components running independently and concurrently, spanning across multiple physical servers.

Now, having a master node where the cluster configuration is stored and other worker nodes that download it from this master node and auto-configure themselves seems to be a simple and elegant solution. However, this solution suffers from a potential problem of the master node being a single point of failure. Even if we assume that the master node is designed to be fault-tolerant, designing a system where a change in the configuration is propagated to all worker nodes dynamically is not straightforward.

Service discovery

Often, to sustain the load and increase the availability of the application, we add more physical servers to the system. The client or worker nodes must know about this change in the cluster memberships and the availability of newer machines that host different services in the cluster. This needs careful design and implementation of logic in the client application itself.

Fault-tolerant

A horizontally scalable distributed system that spans over hundreds and thousands of physical machines is often prone to failures such as hardware faults, system crashes, communication link failures, and so on. These types of failures don't really follow any pattern, and hence, to handle such failures in the application logic and design the system to be fault-tolerant is truly a difficult problem.

Difference between RPM, yum and dnf

RPM

RPM is a package format, as well as a low-level package manager. Low-level package managers do basic things, they will install the package for you, but only if all dependencies are already installed, they will uninstall an installed package you specify and they will upgrade a package if you specify the RPM file you want to upgrade the package with. They will not manage dependencies and repositories for you. RPM and other low-level package managers (like Debian’s dpkg and Slackware’s pkgtools) are completely oblivious of the existence of repositories. As such if a package you are trying to install with it is missing a dependency they cannot search enabled repositories for the dependency, download and install it for you. You will have to do the repository searching yourself and then specify the download URL to RPM.

YUM and DNF

yum and DNF are essentially programs that manage dependencies and repositories and then utilize RPM to do the actual installing, downloading and removing of packages. DNF is yum’s successor in this, its main difference from yum is that it uses some libraries from openSUSE’s ZYpp package manager in an attempt to enhance speed and otherwise improve things (although install speed tests I’ve performed seem to indicate that DNF is actually slower than yum overall).

Conférence "OpenStack in action! 5"

Le mercredi 28 mai 2014, à Paris. Participants : TLC

Liens sur le site d'eNovance : OpenStack in Action!

Impressions : Une journée de promotion d'eNovance (la moitié des intervenants étant de la compagnie) et des solutions commerciales des différents partenaires (Red Hat, Suse…). Des sessions techniques très techniques.

A retenir :

les techniques de tests du projet ;

le processus d'intégration continue d'eNovance ;

je suis le seul à avoir un laptop avec Windows… j'ai honte de le sortir ;

pas mal de gens sont en train de reviewer des patchs (avec Gerritet autres)

09h35 - Accelerate your business in the open hybrid cloud with OpenStack / Bryan Che

Présentation (commerciale) des services cloud de Red Hat.

“Dans 10 ans, rien en IT ne se fera sans OpenStack”

La maintenance représente 80% du budget de l'IT ; OpenStack veut inverser le ratio.

Les mots du jour : “Agile, efficiant, scalable”

RedHat OpenShift PaaS

GearD for containers (docker: isolated apps in a VM) on top of RedHat Linux atomic host

CloudForms (anciennement ManageIQ) : gestion “commerciale” d'un cloud

10h05 - Combining cloud technologies to leverage / Jean Philippe Melet

Présentation commerciale de la solution vicube de la société Econocom

“Marketwise, cloud is a huge oportunity for business”

10h30 - Is OpenStack ready for the enterprise? / Nick Barcet

OpenStack is NOT a product! It's a technology framework. A cloud can be based on OpenStack

Saving money on licensing fee is not a good reason to switch (ex: ESX, licensing is only 10%, 35% human cost)

Good reasons to switch : it's Free software (Adaptability, Security, Sharing, Standard, Hybridate)

“better, quicker, faster on the way to succes”

Stop pre-control craziness: trust is the first enabler of inovation, wich leads to responsability, autonomy and creativity

mesure in end goals, not in milestones

11h50 - OpenStack powered by users / Jonathan Bryce

Présentation renommée “OpenStack global update” qui est un résumé de ce qui s'est dit à Atlanta.

It's a plateform. Apache 2 license

Icehouse: 9th release, 1200 dev (+30%)

OpenStack summit in november in Paris

11h50 - Why OpenStack [...] for private cloud? / Andrew Mitry

Présentation par une personne de NBCUniversal des raisons pour lesquels ils ont choisi OpenStack.

Community is driving the standards

Not locked-in by vendor

API abstraction, IPv6

12h20 - Behind the scene: how we produce OpenStack / Thierry Carrez

Présentation de quelques statistiques et pratiques du projet OpenStack.

130+ git repo, 1.8+ MLOC

principals

if it's not (automatically) tested then it's considered as not working

code review (for everyone)

gate-centric dev (robotic overlord)

time based releases (all the teams keep in sync)

automate everything

challenges

chaos: no offical project goals

task coordination across groups

congestion of the gate (tests in parallel : A, A+B, A+B+C)

rare occurences

community focus

“watercooler effect” : discussions à la machine à café remplacées par IRC et mailing lists

anger (!!)… meet face to face

“biggest software development ever” (?)

14h00 - Easing deployment of Highly available OpenStack cloud / Vincent Untz

Présentation des solutions de haute disponibilité.

High Availability (HA) done using Pacemaker on GNU. Required to reach 99,9% (and more) availability, minimises system downtime, minimises data loss.

Différentes stratégies :

Active/Passive: a server takes over in case of failure

Active/Active: load balancing, DB… (for stateless software)

HA in OpenStack: redondant network, storage…

Good news: guide available, many stateless services. Bad news: difficult, services not easy to set up in active/active (DB)

Pacemaker: “you don't want it, but you need it” (to reach 99,9% SLA)

Hawk: web UI for Pacemaker

14h30 - Bridges and tunnels [...] OpenStack networking / Mark McClain

Présentation très technique du composant réseau d'OpenStack : Neutron.

Why Neutron? Additionnal features, technology agnostique, unified API and small core

Rest of the talk: technical details and implementation

15h00 - Code testing strategies / Chmouel Boujnah

Présentation un peu farfelue de la manière dont les tests sont organisés dans OpenStack.

Unit test: Test Driven Development (TDD), coding style (flake8 on top of pep8)

Integration testing (API)

Performence testing (benchmarking): do hardware performence test first

Scalability testing

regression

compatibility

Pentesting

Usability

Tools and Libraries: DevStack, tox/virtualenv, pbr, testrunner, coverage, testtools, mock, httppretty, six, tempest

15h30 - Nova, Road to Juno / Nikola Dipanov

Présentation un peu confuse de la migration de Nova Network lors de la dernière release.

Main concerns: live upgrades, live migrations

16h30 - OpenStack and Ceph / Sebastien Han

Présentation de Ceph et de son intégration dans OpenStack.

Can be used since IceHouse with all the OpenStack components

17h00 - OpenStack on a silver platter / Emilien Macchi

Présentation des méthodes d'intégration continue (CI) d'OpenStack par la société eNovance. Ce processus est mis en place pour gérer toute la mise à jour, le principal problème étant l'ordre de redémarrage des différents composants.

All the tools developped by eNovance are OpenSource and available on GitHub.

Jenkins: install OpenStack everyday on VM, then use tempest to test. Used to validate upstream packages and installation

eDeploy: to deploy (using rsync) on the real hardware, no new pkg after deployment

Config:

Puppet and serverspec

config-tools supervises puppet

puppet uses modules from stackforge

*Sanity: smoke and tempest

Upgrade: Ansible playbooks

Liens utiles - bookmark UTEC6

PROCEDURE CERTIFICAT CACERT

https://wiki.bioaster.org/_media/ut6/procedure_d_acces_au_wiki.pdf

OWNCLOUD

https://owncloud.bioaster.org/

LE WIKI

https://wiki.bioaster.org

DEMANDE D'OUVERTURE DE COMPTE AU CC

La création de compte se fait depuis la page https://cctools.in2p3.fr/cclogon/

1. Secteur et laboratoire : Pluridisciplinarité> BIOASTER.

2. Choisir un login en accord avec l'utilisateur et spécifier son mail@bioaster

2. Faire signer la demande par Alain Troesch ou Nathalie Garçon.

3. Imprimer la demande et la faxer ou l'envoyer à Ghita Rahal du CCIN2P3, ou la faire passer à NS, AB ou PV qui transmettront en main propre.

4. A la réception du message confirmant la création de compte, créer un mot de passe avec la commande setkpasswd. Attention, seul le Czar mot de passe du groupe bioaster peut créer ou renouveler les mots de passe des membres du groupe. Le Czar actuel est Nicolas Sapay.

5. Transmettre le mot de passe par téléphone ou par écrit à l'utilisateur. L'utilisateur devra changer le mot de passe à la 1re connexion, puis tous les 45 jours.

GITLAB

https://gitlab.in2p3.fr/

Spécifier son mail@bioaster à la création du compte

DEVTOOLS

https://devtools.bioaster.org/

REDMINE

https://devtools.bioaster.org/redmine

Identifiants : AD Windows

GLPI (ticket interne Bioaster)

https://helpdesk.bioaster.org

Identifiants : AD Windows

OTRS CC (Ticket contre le CC)

https://cc-usersupport.in2p3.fr/otrs/customer.pl

Pastebin@CC

http://pastebin.in2p3.fr/

Etherpad@CC

https://etherpad.in2p3.fr/

Réunion du 23 Mars 2017

Personnes présentes

CD

JHA

YM

PDU

GB

Ordre du jour :

Débriefing avec GB sur le BA UID

Use cases création d'échantillons

JHA :

Interviews NeT

Bibliothèques pythons pour ETL

Débriefing avec GB sur le BA UID

Point sur le BA UID adopté.
Pour rappel :
IDProjetBIOASTER+WorkpackageNuméro_IDincrémentalDeLechantillon
Exemple : BA010WP3_12356

Remarques de GB :

On peut ajouter la notion de dangerosité en fin ou début de code par son numéro allant de 1 à 4.

On peut imaginer amener de l'innovation dans ce module en s'interfaçant avec des douchettes à écran qui pourraient alors rapidement afficher des infos d'intérêt au scan de l'échantillon sans pour autant être connecté à un poste.

Clarification des termes Classifications pour chaque Models touchés. Exemple : “type” pour Sample et “origin” pour Bioentity

TODO :

Avertir l'AQ de la décision prise par les experts pour avoir leur GO. On corrélera cette action avec la validation finale du fichier de stockage par les experts (attente du retour de KL)

changer les labels pour les classifications

supprimer la table Bioentity et la ramener à un champs bioentity_classification corrélé à un champs bioentity_json pour les champs dynamiques associés à la valeur de classification bioentity choisie

Récupérer le BA ID projet dans Sciforma via Shibboleth et le capter via auth-shib (PLU)

Use cases création d'échantillons

CD avait proposé de dérouler plusieurs use cases sur cette page. Nous avons très vite compris qu'il serait préférable d'attendre qu'on ait les consensus des classifications Sample et Bioentity pour s'y attaquer.

TODO :

Produire le consensus des classification Sample et Bioentity

Dérouler les Use cases

Faire participer la NeT pour faire des use cases parlant

JHA

Interviews NeT

JHA a présenter ses questions pour ses interviews prévues d'experts.
L'équipe l'a aidé à les affiner et à en rajouter.

Bibliothèques pythons pour ETL

JHA a présenté un tableau comparatif de diverses bibliothèques python existantes. La présentation est sur M (/02_DST/04_UTEC/06_UTEC/Projets/En cours/NoE/2017_Stage_Julie/Interview_Librairies_python _230317.pdf).
–> JHA utilisera Pandas pour interagir avec les fichiers que lui donneront les experts. PDU s'est proposé de lui fournir un peu d'aide si nécessaire.

TODO :

Mise à niveau git

Formation pyenv/virtualenv

Appréhender Pandas

Se faire la main avec les fichiers reçus des experts

Réfléchir à une idée de rendu visuel des clusters produits

Install WSO2_IS server

1. Pre-requis

1. Install oracle open jdk

To run WSO2_IS server, Jdk 1.7 or 1.8 is required. And the default openjdk is not recommended. So we need to install the oracle jdk 1.8 first.

You can find how to install jdk here : https://wiki.bioaster.org/employes/pengfei.liu_bioaster.org/install_jdk

2. Run wso2-is as a linux daemon

In /etc/init.d/, you need create a file wso2d

touch /etc/init.d/wso2d

vim /etc/init.d/wso2d

And put the following code in it.

#! /bin/sh

export JAVA_HOME="/opt/jdk1.8.0_121"
 
startcmd='/opt/wso2is-5.3.0/bin/wso2server.sh start > /var/log/wso2_is/server_status.log &'
restartcmd='/opt/wso2is-5.3.0/bin/wso2server.sh restart > /var/log/wso2_is/server_status.log &'
stopcmd='/opt/wso2is-5.3.0/bin/wso2server.sh stop > /var/log/wso2_is/server_status.log &'
 
case "$1" in
start)
   echo "Starting WSO2 Application Server ..."
   su -c "${startcmd}" 
;;
restart)
   echo "Re-starting WSO2 Application Server ..."
   su -c "${restartcmd}"
;;
stop)
   echo "Stopping WSO2 Application Server ..."
   su -c "${stopcmd}" 
;;
*)
   echo "Usage: $0 {start|stop|restart}"
exit 1
esac

chmod 710 wso2d

Now you need to update the initd to load the wso2d

sudo update-rc.d wso2d defaults

The defaults option in the above command makes the service to start in runlevels 2,3,4 and 5 and to stop in runlevels 0,1 and 6.

2. Deploye WSO2-IS en production

1. Change default key store

Please go here to see more details https://wiki.bioaster.org/employes/pengfei.liu_bioaster.org/wso2_change_https_cert?&#copy_the_new_keystore_and_configure_wso2-is_to_use_the_new_keystore

2. Change host name

Open <IS_HOME>/repository/conf/carbon.xml file.

The private key is used for the HTTPS channel and for the token issuer to sign the issued tokens.

The following section of the carbon.xml should be updated to match your private key information.

<!--
       Host name or IP address of the machine hosting this server
       e.g. www.wso2.org, 192.168.1.10
       This is will become part of the End Point Reference of the
       services deployed on this server instance.
    -->
    <HostName>localhost</HostName>
    <!--
    Host name to be used for the Carbon management console
    -->
    <MgtHostName>localhost</MgtHostName>
    <!--
        The URL of the back end server. This is where the admin services are hosted and
        will be used by the clients in the front end server.
        This is required only for the Front-end server. This is used when seperating BE server from FE server
       -->
    <ServerURL>local:/${carbon.context}/services/</ServerURL>

3. change http and https port

Open <IS_HOME>/repository/conf/tomcat/catalina-server.xml file and change the HTTP and HTTPS ports in the <connector> elements. For example,

<Connector  protocol="org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11NioProtocol"
               port="9763"
               ...
/>
 
<Connector  protocol="org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11NioProtocol"
               port="9443
               scheme="https"
               ...
/>

Instancier une machine sur OpenStack

Créer la VM

Prérequis : être connecté au CC ou avoir configuré son environnement local pour utiliser nova.

La commande pour créer une VM est :

nova boot --key-name=cloudkey --image=CentOS-7 --flavor=m1.tiny --security-groups=default dev-tools

cloudkey est le nom de la clé SSH qui sera autorisée à se connecter sur la VM ;

Centos-7 est le nom de l'image à instancier ;

m1.tiny représente les ressources (CPU, RAM, …) mises à disposition pour cette VM ;

default est la politique de sécurité à appliquer ;

dev-tools est le nom de la VM.

L'état de construction peut être vérifié avec nova list. Cette commande permet aussi de voir l'adresse IP ayant été attribuée à la VM.

Se connecter à la VM

Prérequis : l'utilitaire SSH et un pare-feu laissant passer les connexions.

Une fois démarrée, on peut se connecter à la VM avec la commande : ssh -i .novacreds/cloudkey centos@134.158.37.17.

.novacreds/cloudkey correspond à la clé SSH qui a été enregistrée dans OpenStack (commande keypair-add) avec l'identifiant cloudkey ;

centos est l'utilisateur par défaut de l'image Centos-7 ;

134.158.37.17 est l'adresse IP associée à la VM.

Appliquer la configuration minimale à la VM

Prérequis : les outils git et ansible à disposition.

Bien que la VM soit utilisable telle quelle, il est préférable de lui appliquer les configurations de base de tout serveur BIOASTER. Pour ce faire, on utilise le gestionnaire de configuration ansible.

On récupère les playbooks et les rôles ansible : git clone git@gitlab.in2p3.fr:bioaster/ansible.git.

On crée, dans le dossier cloné, un fichier inventaire avec notre VM :

inventory

[my_group]
my.server.name ansible_host=134.158.37.17 ansible_user=centos

On crée ensuite un playbook minimal pour gérer notre VM :

site.yml

---
 
- name: Configure my VM
  hosts: my_group
  roles:
    - server

Le rôle server va configurer de nombreux éléments parmi lesquels : OpenSSH, NTPd, /etc/hosts, …

On exécute le playbook avec la commande : ansible-playbook -i inventory -l my_group site.yml.

inventory est notre fichier d'inventaire qui remplace celui par défaut (/etc/ansible/inventory) ;

my_group est le groupe auquel on veut se limiter (option -l) ;

site.yml est le playbook à utiliser.

Une fois configuré, il est possible d'accéder à la machine avec les utilisateurs définis par le rôle. Ceux-ci sont pour le moment définis par la variable system_users dans le fichier roles/server/defaults/main.yml.